Okay, so in the period 1800 to 1848,
democracy in America got a big shot of
political growth hormones. And while I
don't endorse such a practice for human
beings, it's never a bad thing to beef
up the franchise. So if you're ready to
get them brain cows milked, let's get to
it. Okay, now democracy, in case you
don't know, doesn't expand itself. Now,
if a government opens the franchise to
more people, it's typically because
they're forced into it. And by the way,
you'll see that word franchise a lot in
this course, and it just means the right
to vote. And it's important, so stick
that one deep in your brain, folks. And
to be clear, the debate over voting
rights did not begin in this period. It
was a debate that raged between the
earliest political parties, and you had
the Federalists in particular getting a
little twitchy about expanding the
franchise too much on account of they
fear the implications of too much
democracy. Regardless, let's talk about
the two major causes of the expansion of
the franchise during this period. First,
and arguably most important, was the
panic of 1819. Now, we talked about this
in a previous video, but by way of
reminder, this was an economic
depression directly caused by risky and
irresponsible practices carried out by
the Second Bank of the United States.
And again to further remind you, this is
the national stinking bank for the whole
country, like the bank of the United
States. And they were getting all kinds
of reckless with their policies in the
years leading up to the panic.
Basically, the bank loaned out more
money than people could afford to pay
back, especially western farmers. When
that speculative gamble failed, it
sparked the panic of 1819 and things got
uh real bad. Many western farmers lost
their land to foreclosure, as did many
southern farmers. And then northern
manufacturers and laborers suffered as
well since they were made to endure a
precipitous decline in the export of
food and raw materials from the other
regions. It was to use the technical
historical term a stanky economic
dumpster fund. But that stank revealed
an even deeper stank. Namely, the vast
majority of Americans who were hit
hardest by this depression could not
vote and therefore could not hold their
representatives responsible for the
crisis. And so as a direct result of the
situation, a growing movement to expand
voting rights gathered steam and the
main call to action was to remove
property qualifications for voting.
Because whether a person was propertied
or not, they could still endure hardship
on account of these policies. And hey,
before I tell you what happened as a
result, let me just mention that if your
A Bush grade is a stanky dumpster fire,
then you might want to check out my
Himler review guide. It's going to help
you get an A in your class and a five on
your exam in May, and it's going to help
you do it as fast as possible. It's got
metric buttloadads of resources to that
end. So if that's the kind of thing
you're into, check that link in the
description. Anyway, the second cause of
the expansion of the franchise was the
democratic pattern of the western
states. So, the leader of this charge
was the Democratic Republican Martin Van
Burnern, whose passion for democracy was
second only to his passion for
maintaining his righteous facial hair.
Anyway, Van Beern led the public charge
in New York for universal white male
suffrage. And a significant part of his
argument, not to mention the many
disenfranchised Americans who likewise
argued, was that universal white male
suffrage was already present in the
Western Frontier States. And that was
true. They organized their territories
and then their states on the assumption
that every white man had the right to
vote. And this was especially important
to them since they had lower populations
and wanted to attract settlers by
dangling that sweet, sweet franchise out
in front of their noses. And so by 1825,
a majority of states on the eastern
coast had either eliminated or
significantly reduced property
qualifications for voting, even though
such a move was opposed by the property
elite who had formerly held the sole
privilege of the franchise. And in most
cases, this was settled by conversation
and debate. But in at least one case,
the passion of the common man to gain
the franchise nearly erupted into
violence, as it did in an event known as
Door's Rebellion in Rhode Island. Now,
Rhode Island was a singular case of a
state government not having written a
new constitution after the Revolutionary
War. Instead, they still used their
royal colonial charter as a governing
document. And that was very on brand for
Rhode Island. Like, they never played by
anybody else's rules. Anyway, the Rhode
Island charter only allowed propertied
men to vote. But by the 1840s, there
were loud calls for a new state
constitution that removed property
requirements, but the legislature
refused to consider it since it meant
the possibility of common factory
workers and immigrants voting.
>> The horror.
>> But then in 1841, proponents of the
expansion of the franchise organized a
convention in which they wrote a new
state constitution that allowed for
universal white male suffrage and they
elected a lawyer named Thomas Door to
become the governor. Now, to be clear,
setting up a rival government like this
was not in fact legal. And so, President
John Tyler went ahead and interpreted
this development as treason and sent in
federal troops to crush the illegal
state government. Now, I wish I could
tell you that there was a salacious and
fantastic battle, but in reality, when
the federal troops arrived, Door's
movement fizzled uh real quick and that
was kind of the end of it. But the point
is, Door's rebellion is an illustration
of just how deep the passions ran among
disenfranchised Americans in the pursuit
of voting rights. Anyway, in 1842, Rhode
Island ratified a new state
constitution, which did indeed expand
the franchise, but not as far as many
wanted it to. It dropped the land
requirements and in a somewhat
surprising move mandated that all Rhode
Island men could vote, black men
included, so long as they had at least
$134 worth of personal property.
However, it's important to remember here
that while this expansion of democracy
party opened up opportunities for
political participation to some
Americans, there were plenty of
Americans left out of that party. Women,
for example, were not included in the
franchise since they were understood to
be primarily dependent on men and not
their own independent entities. Thanks,
cult of domesticity. And then for the
most part, neither were black men
included in the franchise on account of
fears of interracial marrying and the
possibility of their electing black
leaders to represent them. So even
though the north held a significant
population of free blacks, nearly all of
them were legally prevented from voting
since states still had a lot of power to
limit the voting rights of their
populations. Okay, now let's consider
the effects of this expansion of
democracy. And the big one here is that
there were major changes in America's
political parties. You see, when you
open the right to vote to more people,
politicians and political parties have
to adjust their platforms in order to
appeal to those new voters. And because
they have interests that are likely
different from all those propertied
elite men who used to dominate the
voting booth, then well, you know,
parties have to change in order to
account for that. Okay. Now, the last
time we talked about political parties,
we spent time with the Federalist and
the Democratic Republicans, both of
which emerged at the very foundation of
the United States. But by the 1820s, the
Federalists were altogether dead. And it
was their opposition to the very popular
war of 1812 that caused them to fall out
of favor with the voting public. Like
they really hated that war. They went so
far in their opposition that they met at
the Hartford Convention and proposed an
entire New England secession from the
United States. But unfortunately for
them, the US won that war. And the
country was positively foaming at the
mouth with nationalism and good
feelings. And so the Federalists were
seen as out of touch with the vibe of
American happiness. So that left the US
with a single political party, namely
the Democratic Republicans. But by the
presidential election of 1824, the party
was split into rival factions, the
Democrats and the National Republicans.
Now, to be clear, these were not new
parties at this point, but the split
would ultimately lead that way. Anyway,
due to the bitter division in the party,
they could not agree on a presidential
candidate to put forward for the
election of 1824. And so, four
candidates emerged. John Quincy Adams,
Andrew Jackson, Henry Clay, and William
Crawford. And as the contest revved up,
it really became a contest between Adams
and Jackson. Okay, so here's where we
tie all of it together. Remember that by
this time, voting rights had been
significantly expanded to most white
men, the majority of whom were not
elite, but rather common folk. And that
meant that candidates needed to appeal
to this enormous new voting block. And
here's where I tell you that Jackson
understood the assignment and Adams did
not. You see, Adams was old school and
so relied on the tradition of allowing
other people to campaign for him. And
they emphasized his rich history of
international diplomacy, which had
expanded US territory. Absolute
snorefest. But Jackson, on the other
hand, appealed directly to the masses
and emphasized his record as a war hero.
Plus, he represented the growing Western
population and branded himself as the
anti- elite candidate who shared the
concerns of the common man. And so,
since many more common men were able to
vote, Jackson's appeal was by far more
popular, and he won both the popular
vote and the electoral college vote over
Adams. However, it's worth mentioning
that the growth of slavery played a
significant role in Jackson's vote count
since the three-fifths compromise
ensured more electors to slave states.
So Jackson won the electoral college,
but not so fast, my dear pupil. It turns
out that while Jackson did in fact get
the most electoral votes, he did not win
a majority. And in that case, the
constitution dictates that the president
must be chosen by the House of
Representatives. Now, Henry Clay, who
was never a serious contender for this
election, was nevertheless the speaker
of the house. And he urged his
supporters to back Adams and they did
so. And Adams was elected over the much
more popular Jackson. And if that wasn't
suspicious enough, Adams made a real PR
mistake and appointed Clay as the
Secretary of State. And at that, Jackson
and his supporters cried foul and called
this election a corrupt bargain. And he
went to work getting ready for the next
election. Anyway, in the end, Adams
didn't make many notable achievements
while in office since he was opposed at
almost every turn by a Congress
controlled by those who disagreed with
him. And that brings us to the election
of 1828, which was a rematch between
Adams and Jackson. And the tensions
generated in this race created the
conditions for the formal split of the
Democratic Republicans into two new
parties. The Democrats were led by
Andrew Jackson and the National
Republicans were led by Adams at first
and then later by Henry Clay. Now, the
National Republicans would be
short-lived and soon replaced by the
Wigs, but I'm going to tell you about
that in another video. Anyway, again,
Adams really didn't understand the
assignment when it came to campaigning
in the era of new expanded democracy. He
took the old posture of waiting to be
asked to serve his country. But Jackson
again took his arguments to the masses
and campaigned for himself to become
president. He held massively popular
rallies all over the country where he
spoke directly to the people and his
campaign team even branded Jackson as
old hickory to communicate to the masses
that he was tough just as his war record
suggested. And with a significantly
expanded electorate filled not with
elites, but with common men who are wage
workers and farmers, Jackson's strategy
won the day and he became president. And
this was significant in many ways, not
least because he was the first president
that was not from Virginia or
Massachusetts, but rather from the West,
which indicated the shifting nature of
national politics during this period.
Okay, you can click here to watch my
other videos from unit 4, or you can
click here to grab my A Push Heimler
review guide, which has everything you
need to study as fast as possible. I'm
glad you came around, and I'll catch you
on the flip-flop. Himler out.